Welcome in to the drive time podcast.
Alongside me is new Dolphins quarterback
Malik Willis. Malik, welcome in, man.
>> I appreciate you for having me.
>> We're very excited to have you in here.
And uh just so far, I mean, this is the
first time since high school you've had
a chance to choose your your next
venture in football, right? What's the
process been like for you in free
agency?
>> Uh it's a little bit like recruiting,
but uh also you kind of have an idea of
what you're getting. Not like high
school. high school, you don't know what
you're getting in college, but uh free
agency, you you you know what you know
happens in the league and what people
expect of you, what your job will be,
and it's just figuring out a role in a
place that you think will fit. And I
think this has been the place for me.
>> Yeah, we love to hear that. And I love
seeing the uh the Pat McAfee interview
when you're on the field working out
before uh you you know, you announced
that you're coming to the Miami
Dolphins. How's the offseason been going
for you so far? Working pretty hard, it
looks like.
>> Oh yeah, it's been awesome. That's how
you, you know, keep away from all the
the media and all the thought processes
on what you're going to do, you know?
So, you just try to stay focused in in
the grind and do what you can to prepare
yourself for the next opportunity.
>> So, you arrive here, had a chance to
meet the folks so far and doing all your
media stuff and getting out of the way,
but what does it mean to you to come
here and have a chance to to prove that
you're the guy for the Miami Dolphins?
>> I think it's awesome. I think it's a
blessing and it's just a part of the
journey and the story that's been
written for me and uh I'm more than
grateful that they even give me the
opportunity to prove something like that
and I'll do my best to you know make
them right.
>> Yeah, those guys you're talking about of
course Jeff Hafley and John Eric
Sullivan and Jeff Hafley told some great
stories so far and his his various media
spots that he's done since he got hired
here talking about you a little bit and
he talked about going up against you in
practice on the scout team, right? Uh
just first though real quick, what can
you tell us about your relationship with
both coach Halfley and John Eric
Sullivan?
>> I mean both great dudes and uh they they
know how to win. They know what it takes
to win and they I have great faith that
they'll do everything they can to put us
in position to be successful going
against a half every day. It was awesome
cuz he he gets very energetic. He's he's
going to let you know when he feels like
the defense is doing great. So uh you
should see uh having the coaches battle
against each other. It should be really
awesome.
>> The smile on your face says it all, man.
fired up to work with him, right?
>> Yeah. You love that type of energy and
you love when people care about what
they do and it's not just, you know, a
business relationship. He has a personal
relationship with all the guys and I
respect that more than anything.
>> He's touched on that quite a bit in
those various media spots I talked about
and you've had a chance to watch him,
you know, do his thing. As far as what
the Dolphins are getting in terms of a
leader from Coach Halfley, what are we
getting with Jeff Hafley in terms of
commanding a room and being the leader
of this football team?
>> I mean, he's a guy you can get behind
when he speaks. uh he's definitely
adamant in what he wants to talk about
and he'll make it so he can communicate
with each and every person no matter how
different they may need it to uh
understand and I think he does a good
job with you know delegating and making
sure that we're all you know leading
each other at the same time.
>> Another one of those uh talking points
we've heard about is just the culture of
toughness and hard work and they're
going to they're going to grind their
way through this this thing for the
results in the end. How do you
contribute to that culture of toughness
mentality and hard work? uh just doing
everything that I can to do the right
thing each and every day. I feel like
that's where it starts. It starts with
you know putting the work in and you
know you can't control all the other
stuff but it toughness is a mindset.
It's not more than anything than that.
It's if you're out trying to get back if
you're you know banged up still fighting
through it and doing what you can
because we're all going to be tired.
We're all going to be hurting. We're all
going, you know, that's the name of the
game. But it's uh fighting through and
persevering.
>> That's a huge part of this league,
right? The physical traits are great but
you have to be wired a certain way to
excel in this league. has that kind of
been your experience four years in
>> thousand% cuz there's so many ups and
downs and so many things that are
uncontrollable and yeah you can't be uh
easily swayed I want to say that you got
to have your mind fixed in a certain way
and you have to be willing to handle the
good with the bad.
>> So I want to dig into this a little bit
further here and this is a long question
so I apologize I'm going to go through
it here. I did some background on just
kind of getting to know you a little bit
and going back to the famous scouting
combine video when you're giving away
your clothes right before the the
workouts there and I read some quotes
when you had a start against the Titans,
your former team back in 24 and the
questions that the re reporters were
asking were like are you excited to get
revenge and you didn't take that that
path? you talked about being thankful
for the opportunity to get your start in
the league with those guys and then
going back to college you know the
patience to wait for your opportunity
going to Liberty and eventually you know
excelling there and it just kind of
seems like nothing really bothers you
like nothing really gets to you and
again that jives with what we've heard
from both Half and Sully so the question
after all that is how did you develop
that mindset where does that come from
where it's instilled to you just roll
the punches and can control what you can
control
>> I mean gratefulness and just
understanding who my God is and uh
through for all the ups and downs, he
going to be there. No matter whether I
throw five touchdowns or three picks,
he's going to be there. And I I can
trust that every part of the journey, it
works out in the end for the process.
And I wouldn't have Green Bay without
going through Tennessee and I wouldn't
have Miami without either one. So you
can say, you know, the good and the bad,
it all works together to form, you know,
what it needs to be.
>> Our journey shapes us in every single
way. And that's kind of the next part of
the question was, you know,
>> what did you learn going from Tennessee?
where you you get a few starts there,
right? Your rookie season, don't play
your second year, but then you go to
Green Bay and it's a different role.
You're you're the backup to Jordan Love
there and you play really really good
football when you got your chances
there. What did you learn through the
process and through your development of
playing the position there in Green Bay?
>> I mean, really just having some time to
sit back and learn. Uh it was a lot
different from what I was doing in
college. So, getting thrown in the fire
early wasn't, you know,
probably helpful, but it it happened and
you got to deal with the results of
that. And uh I think just being able to
sit back and learn and uh just see the
game unfold many many different times,
different ways, different games, and
even at practice and get to try so many
different things. I think that helped me
to be more confident in my abilities
because it was never really physical.
Making sure that I was prepared every
day mentally and trusting in what I was
seeing. Not only knowing what you're
doing because you can know what you're
doing and not trust it, right? Uh but
just making sure I was trusting it. Is
it easier when you don't have like
obviously you're getting ready for a
game on Sundays but you're not starting.
Is it easier in that role to further
develop like mechanics and just the film
work and kind of like you talk about
trusting what you're seeing. Does that
stuff come easier when you don't have
the stress of playing every Sunday?
>> I wouldn't say so because you got to be
prepared to go in at any time because if
you have that mindset, you're not going
to be prepared when it's time for you to
go in because it's like one play and
then boom. Uh just like when we played
the Giants last season, he ain't got
hurt in like the first quarter or
something and I had to go in and it's
like, "Oh, well, you're in there." And
there's no, "Hey, give him a second to
warm up or you know, only run these
plays cuz he's uh he's chilling." No,
like you got to be ready to go cuz at
the end of the day, it's about wins and
losses in this league and everybody
contributes to them.
>> Yeah. The Giants didn't care that you
were coming off the bench in that game
like it didn't matter.
>> Oh, no. They they was playing good
defense.
>> That's right. So, you made your first
start for the Packers just 20 days after
you arrived there. And Matt Lafler
really praised your ability to help keep
his long call sheets available to get
through all the shifts and the motions.
And I'm curious, how did that sort of I
guess baptism by fire, if you will, of
getting out there right away. How did
that accelerate your learning curve?
>> I mean, it was uh similar to a system I
had previously run in uh Tennessee. Uh,
so I was I picked it up a little easier
than when I was coming out of college
to, you know, my first NFL system. So it
was just making sure the lingo was
right, making sure that I was confident
in the call and knew what everything
meant. But, uh, it was very, uh, helpful
that I had that prior knowledge.
>> Yeah. So, that was my next question was,
you know, come to Bobby Slowick's
offense where he has experience in
similar styles of offensive attacks. And
we always see whether it's like media or
fans, you hear like, oh, he's played
that offense before even though he's a
different coach. So, it's going to be
easy for him, but I don't think it's
always just like as easy as just picking
up one place and going to the next,
right? So, I wanted to hear from someone
that's been there and done that. How
does playing in you mentioned the
Tennessee offense, then Matt Lafleur,
how does that prepare you for Bobby
Sloick's offense here in Miami?
>> I mean, this is my fourth offense, so I
I understand it is not it's not easy
though. Still, regardless, you you have
to get in, you have to do the work, you
have to learn it, and you have to master
it because that's what it's about. It's
not just about knowing, it's about being
able to go out there and it's um 80,000
people yelling and you got to be able to
recall it and spit it out and make sure
everybody know what they doing. And I
think that's what it's about. And I
think it's definitely helpful coming
from a similar system, but at the same
time, you got to take it from zero. You
got to start over and wipe it all away
and learn something new.
>> One of the fun parts I about watching
your tape was just watching you run
around a little bit, man. The zone read
against the Ravens last year around the
corner. take that thing out for a 22
yard touchdown. And I'm watching plays
like that and I'm thinking we got Malik,
we got Devon Aan back there. When you
think about how your guys' speed
compared together in the back field, how
does that challenge defenses, do you
think?
>> I think it's tough. Uh you can really
stress the field and uh you got to
defend every part of the field and
that's hard for guys to do because you
want to, you know, focus on whatever
guys can't do. I mean, you you want to
take away what they can do best. So, I
think it's it's awesome and we'll see
how it plays out. Same with Jaylen Wadd
too, right? Big play receiver down the
field.
>> There's a lot of guys that are ready to
make plays. I see, you know, and then
walking through the building, it's like,
dang, these guys are ready to go.
They're working hard. You see them in
the weight room. You see them in the
training room are getting back. And I
think it's awesome.
>> Well, OTAAS cannot come fast enough. Two
more quick questions for you here real
quick. Just kind of a a general
description. What are the Dolphins
getting in Malik Willis?
>> They getting a a god-fearing man.
They're getting a quarterback that's
willing to do anything to go out there
and win the game. again, a guy who's
going to always have his teammates back
and his coach's backs, then somebody
gonna give it all they got.
>> We'd love to hear that. And just to kind
of close things out here, we talked a
lot of football with you. You talked
about the facility before we came on the
air here. I want to ask you, outside of
the game of football, what are you most
excited about for your time in South
Florida here coming up?
>> I mean, there's so many things. I mean,
the weather is great every day. Uh so
much food everywhere and and the water
is right there. I mean, there's no and
all the different cultures and types of
people that are around here, you just
see so much. So, I'm excited for it all.
>> That's new Dolphins quarterback Malik
Willis. Malik, thank you for your time
today, man. Appreciate.
>> Yes, sir. Appreciate you.